The Life of Muhammadﷺ, The Madinan Period, Volume 1
By Imam Anwar Al_Awlaki,
اَعُوْذُ بِاللهِ مِنَّ الشِّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيْمِ ۝ بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْمَ۝
اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ
We're carrying on with lessons from Uhud(أحَد).
Why were youth such as Rafiyah Bin Khateej(رافع بن خديج) and Samurah Bin Jundub(سَمُرَةْ بن جندب)
and some others like Abdullah Bin Umar(عبدالله بن عمر) and Al-Bara'a Bin Aazib(البراء بن عازب),
why were they so eager to join the fight.
One might argue that the reason is that they belong to a militant society.
I mean, one could say that,
well that was the lifestyle of the Arabs, this was a warlike people,
all what they did was fight, fight, fight.
So it's not really strange that these kids would want to join in war and battle
because that's part of being a man in Arabia.
When one could argue from this point of view.
But one could respond back by saying that, that's not necessarily the case.
Because when youngsters such as Abdullah Bin Umar(عبدالله بن عمر), Al-Bara'a Bin Aazib(البرآء بن عازب)
Samoorah(سَمُرَةْ) and Rafiah(رافع) wanted to join the army,
on the other hand, we have about 300, who defected.
So, it's not all about the society and this being a society of warriors that's not really true.
The issue here is Eeman(ايمان),
the ones who had Eeman(ايمان) and the ones who didn't have it
the ones who had Eeman(ايمان) would so eager to join
and the ones who didn't have it was so eager to run away.
Abdullah Bin Obaeye(عبدالله بن اُبَيئ) and 300 of his men defected, in the day of Uhud(أحَد),
withdrew, they refuse to fight.
And this was the case in many of the other battles,
they refused to join in Tabook(تبوك), they refused to join in Al-Khandaq(الخندق).
So, they run away in times of fear.
And I use the word defected a lot.
And again, probably in one sense, this is the right word to use,
because them withdrawing is really them being on the side of the enemy.
But I don't want it to be understood that they defected to the enemy side,
that's not the case,
I mean, they withdrew back to Uhud(أحَد), they didn't go and fight to the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
But even though they weren't participating in the fight, but one can say that
they were part of the enemy's army
because they would support them with information, they would act as spies for them.
So, don't take the word literal, it does have a correct meaning,
but not in a literal sense.
It's not that they actually physically defected to the enemy's army.
Next lesson one can see one of the characteristics of the Munafiqeen(منافقين) in this battle.
They refused to fight in Uhud(أحَد), because of fear of death.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ came back,
and he wanted to pursue Abu Sufiyaan(ابوسفيان),
in what is referred to Ghazwa Hamra'a Al-Asad(غزوة حمراء الاسد).
The Munafiqeen(منافقين) in this time wanted to join
but Rasool Allah ﷺ this time refused to allow them to join.
He said only the ones who joined me in Uhud(أحَد), can join me now.
And why did they want to join in Hamra Al-Asad(حمراء الاسد), because
they thought there is a good possibility of winning.
So, there could be some booties of war, to get some of those spoils.
So, this is a characteristic of Munafiqeen(منافقين),
they want to take the worldly benefits from Islam,
but they refuse to pay the demands of Islam.
They want the gains, but they don't want the pains.
They want Ghanimah(غنيمه), but they don't want to fight.
So, this mindset of being a Muslim when it's convenient
and giving it up, when I'm demanded sacrifice
is a sign of hypocrisy.
And it applies to many situations,
and it's very dangerous,
and one should try to check up, themselves and see if that's the case
do I become enthusiastic to join in Islamic activities
when I feel that there's a worldly benefit for me, in it
but when it becomes demanding then I give it up.
For example,
you might know some parents, who are very happy about Islam,
when it comes to the part of Islam that talks about children being obedient to their parents
and respecting their parents and the rights of the parents being second to Allahعَزّوجَلّ,
and all of those Aayaat(آيات) in Qur'an and Hadith(حديث) of Rasool Allah ﷺ
that tell them to take care of their moms and dads
so they love that part of Islam.
However, when it comes to the part of Islam that tells their son to go and for example, fight Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله عَزّوجَلّ),
No, they don't want that part and they don't want their children to hear about that part.
So, I love Islam, when it's gonna tell my sons to be submissive,
but I don't like it when it tells them to go and give up their lives.
Or, for example, the husband who loves the Ahadith(احاديث) of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
He said; If I was going to tell a woman to make Sujood(سجود) to anyone other than Allah,
then I would tell her, to make Sujood(سجود) to her husband.
And if the husband goes to bed and he's upset with his wife,
then the angels will curse the wife until the morning
and he would repeat all of those Ahadith(احاديث).
But when it comes to the Ahadith(احاديث) of Rasool Allah ﷺ, being kind to his wives
when it comes to the stories of the Sahabah(صحابه) being kind to their wives
he wants to hide those away.
Some scholars, for example, they love to talk about how you should respect the scholar
and how you should obey the scholar and listen to their fatwah(فتوى)
and not disagree with them, and you should honor them.
But then the scholar would shy away from the parts of Islam that tell them that they need to speak the truth,
they need to speak the whole truth,
they should hide nothing from it
and they should speak the truth even if they're going to have to pay the price with, their own lives.
So this duality, of wanting to be a Muslim, when it's convenient
and trying to cover up the other parts is not a good thing.
And as we see here, its the sign of Nifaaq(نفاق), so one needs to be careful
and make sure that they don't belong to this category of people.
ادخُلُوا فِي السِّلمِ كَافَّةً
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says, you take Islam in its entirety.
You don't take some parts and leave others that's the sign of the People of the Book.
They believed in, part of the book and they rejected others,
so we have to accept it all.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ, when he took Baiyah(بيعة) from Al-Ansaar(الانصار) the Baiyah(بيعة) was
اَطَّاعَهْ فِيْ الْمَنْشَط وَالْمَكرَهْ
You obey me in times of ease and in times of difficulty.
It's not when you like it, and then you neglect it when you don't.
You have to take the whole package, as it is.
Next lesson, Ibn Al-Qayyim(ابن قيم) says;
that one of the benefits of Uhud(أحَد) is
اِسْتِخْرَاجُ عُبُوْدِيَّة اُوْلِيَآءِهِ وَحِزْبِهِ فِي السَّرَّآءِ وَ الضرَّآءْ
فَاِذَا ثَبَتُ عَلَى الطَّاعَتِ وَالْعُبُوْدِيَّةْ فِيْمَا يُحِبُّوْنَ وَ يَكْرَهُوْنْ فَمْ عَبِيْدُوْ حَقًا
وَلَيْسُ كَمَنْ يَعَبْدُاللهَ عَلَى حَرْفٍ وَاحِدْ مِنَّ السَّرَّآءِ وَنْعْمَ وَالْعَافِيَّه فَقَطْ
So, one of the lessons of Uhud(أحَد) is to show the servitude of the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم,
that they are willing to worship Allahعَزّوجَلّ in times of ease and in times of difficulty.
So, if they are firm and steadfast on the religion on both situations,
that's a sign of true servitude, Uboodiyah (عبودية).
And that's unlike people who only worship Allahعَزّوجَلّ on one condition,
you know, they're program to only worship Allah, if things are tough
they only program to worship Allah, if things are easy,
but they don't have the combination of both.
So, sometimes people only remember Allahعَزّوجَلّ when things get tough
then they start making Dua(دُعَا), O Allah,
for example all of those Bachelors out there.
They're making Dua(دعا) in every Salah(صلاة), in every Sujood(سجود) O Allah, I want to get married,
they would pray Qayyam Ul-Lail(قيام اليل),
they would make this Dua(دعا) between Azaan(اذان) and Iqaamah(اقامه),
they would make this Dua(دعا), when they're making Eitkaaf(اعتكاف),
they would do it on the night of the 27th.
O Allah I want to get married.
And as soon as they get married, they stop making Dua(دعا).
So, that's an example of somebody who only worships Allahعَزّوجَلّ when things are difficult,
but when things get easy, they forget about Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
Like the story Allah mentions in Qur'an, of the people who are in the middle of the sea
and the storm picks up and they feel that they're going to die
and there's no one to ask except Allahعَزّوجَلّ you're in the middle of nowhere, you're in the middle of the ocean.
Your only refuge is Allahعَزّوجَلّ
so they make Dua(دعا) to Allahعَزّوجَلّ they don't make Dua(دعا) to their idols false gods,
they make Dua(دعا) to Allah.
And when Allah delivers them to safety,
then they go back and make Sujood(سجود) to their idols, he also says;
اِنَّه’ اِذَا امتَحَنَهُمْ بِالْغَلَبَة وَالْكَثْرَةْ
وَالْهزِيْمَهْ ذَلُّوْا وَ انكَسرُوْا وَخَضعوا
فَاسْتَوْجَبُوْا مِنْه’ الْعِزَّةْ وَالْنَصْر
فَاِنَّ خُلْعَةً النَّصْرِ اِنَّمَا تَكُوْنُ مَعَ ولاية الذل وَالْاِنْكِسَارْ
He said, that Allahعَزّوجَلّ tested them by them being defeated, and humiliated.
And weaken so that made them humble themselves in front of Allahعَزّوجَلّ
and humiliate themselves in front of Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
And that is when Allahعَزّوجَلّ responds to your Dua(دعا),
when you humble yourself in front of Allahعَزّوجَلّ
and you show Him true servitude that is when Allahعَزّوجَلّ responds to your Dua(دعا).
So, Allahعَزّوجَلّ said about Badr(بدر);
وَلَقَدْ نَصَرَكُمُ اللَّهُ بِبَدْرٍ وَأَنْتُمْ أَذِلَّةٌ ۖ
Allahعَزّوجَلّ gave you victory in Badr(بدر), when you were weak
While in Hunain(حنين)
وَيَوْمَ حُنَيْنٍ ۙ إِذْ أَعْجَبَتْكُمْ كَثْرَتُكُمْ فَلَمْ تُغْنِ عَنْكُمْ شَيْئًا
While in Hunain(حنين) because you are dependent on your numbers you lost.
He also says,
and this will be our last lesson that we talked about in the Battle of Uhud(أحَد)
اِنَّ وَقْعَتْ اُحَدْ كَانَتْ مُقَدِّمَهْ وَيَرْحَاسًا بَيْنَ يَدَيْه مَوْتْ رَسُوْل الله
Uhud(أحَد), was a preparation for the most catastrophic event that will ever happen to the Muslims.
Because this event is so great, they needed to be prepared for it.
And that is the death of Rasool Allah ﷺ
and since Rasool Allah ﷺ was everything for Sahabah(صحابه) in terms of Islam.
You know, they learned Islam from him, he was their source.
They didn't have any books to go and consult.
They didn't have any scholars to go and talk to, they didn't have any Jama'at(جماعات)
to recruit them and teach them about Islam.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was their source and their only source.
So, he was their father, he was everything for them.
So, for them to lose him is not gonna be an easy thing
it's going to be a huge setback and it will cause a serious psychological affect on the hearts of the Muslims,
so they need to be prepared for that.
And that preparation was through this false rumor that spread around on the battleground in Uhud(أحَد),
that Rasool Allah ﷺ has died
and then the Ayah(آية) was revealed,
وَمَا مُحَمَّدٌ إِلَّا رَسُولٌ قَدْ خَلَتْ مِنْ قَبْلِهِ الرُّسُلُ ۚ أَفَإِنْ مَاتَ أَوْ قُتِلَ انْقَلَبْتُمْ عَلَىٰ أَعْقَابِكُمْ ۚ
Muhammad(محمد) is a messenger,
He is but a messenger and there have been many messengers before him
so if he dies you shouldn't fall back on your heels and retreat
you should carry on, forward with the message,
so Allahعَزّوجَلّ prepared them through this Ghazwa(غزوة).
So these are lessons from the Battle of Uhud(أحَد).
We'll talk about events between Al-Uhud(أحَد) and Al-Khandaq(اَلْخَنْدق).
Number one;
Rasool Allah ﷺ heard news that Bannu Asad(بنو اسد) are mobilizing forces to attack Madina
these are tribes in Najd(نجد) and they were headed by Tulaiha Al-Asdi(طليحة الاسدي).
And this man is this man is quite fascinating.
His story is interesting, he started out by fighting against Rasool Allah ﷺ
and then becoming Muslim after that
and then after Rasool Allah ﷺ passes away,
he apostates and claims to be a prophet
and then after that, he changes his mind and becomes a Muslim again
and he fights Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
That was the end of his life, he was Mujahid(مجاهد).
So, he is kind of experienced it at all Tulaiha Al-Asdi(طليحة الاسدي).
Any way he was recruiting men to fight Rasool Allah ﷺ
and Rasool Allah ﷺ as we said he would strike them, take them by surprise.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ sent an army led by Abu Salama(ابوسلمه)
and Abu Salama(ابوسلمه), by the way, was injured in the Battle of Uhud(أحَد)
So he went out in this Sariyyah(سرية)
and the enemy was defeated and he came back with a lot of cattle
and but his injury, which was almost going to heal,
now erupted again and he died, Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله), this is Abu Salama(ابوسلمه).
Another tribe was mobilizing, forced to fight Rasool Allah ﷺ
and these were Hudail(هذيل),
and their leader was Khalid Bin Sufiaan Al-Hudali( خالد بن سفيان الهذلي)
Rasool Allah ﷺ said,
Khalid Bin Sufiaan Al-Hudali( خالد بن سفيان الهذلي) is recruiting an army to fight us.
So, go and kill him.
These orders were delivered to Abdullah Bin Unais رضي الله عنه
who was from the tribe of Juhainah(جهينة).
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him that Hudail(هذيل) are gathering men,
under the leadership of Khalid Bin Sufiaan Al-Hudali( خالد بن سفيان الهذلي), so go and kill him.
Abdullah Bin Unais(عبدالله بن انيس) said; Can you describe him for me,
so that I will know him, I will recognize him, because he never saw him before.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him, if you see him, you will tremble.
This man Khalid Bin Sufiaan(خالد بن سفيان), if you see him you would tremble.
Possibly that could be because this man Khalid Bin Sufiaan(خالد بن سفيان) was such a powerful figure
that whenever anybody who see him, he would tremble.
Abdullah Bin Unais(عبدالله بن انيس), said I never trembled for the sight of anyone
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him but if you see Khalid Bin Sufiaan(خالد بن سفيان), you would tremble.
So, this tells you that Abdullah Bin Unais(عبدالله بن انيس) was the right person to choose.
He was a courageous man, he wasn't somebody who would fear others.
So he said, I never trembled because of anyone.
But this was going to be a special sign
in which, he would be able to recognize who is Khalid Bin Al-Hudail( خالد بن الهذلي)
So, Abdullah Bin Unais(عبدالله بن انيس) said, I carried my sword, and I went out.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ told him that he's gathering the men in Uranah(عرنة) in Arafaat(عرفات).
So, he was gathering them close to Makkah, close to where his tribe lives.
And obviously, that territory is all supportive of the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
So, he is recruiting an army so he opens up a camp
and he's recruiting men to that camp.
Abdullah Bin Unais رضي الله عنه said, I was walking towards this man and when I saw him, I shivered.
So, I knew that this man is Khalid Bin Sufiaan(خالد بن سفيان).
And he was with some women trying to find a camp ground for them.
These were his women wives, daughters, sisters, whatever, women from his family.
So he was with them trying to find for them a camp.
So, he walked towards him and he said it was time for Asar(عصر).
And I was worried that my fight with him could preoccupy me from Salah(صلاة).
I mean Allah Ho Alam(الله اعلم) how long this fight will take.
So, it could preoccupy me from Salah(صلاة), I could be killed.
And since it is already time for Asr(عصر), I need to pray Asr(عصر),
but the problem is, how can you pray Asr(عصر) in the presence of this man?
I mean he would recognize that he's a Muslim.
So, he said, I was praying while I was walking towards him
and my Sujood(سجود) and Rukooh(ركوع) would be movement of my head.
He would move his head, and that would be his Rukooh(ركوع) and Sujood(سجود).
And he said, when I reached him, he said, and who is the man, who are you?
Abdullah Bin Unais(عبدالله بن انيس) said, I am a Bedouin Arab, who heard about your plans to fight Muhammad(محمد).
So I came to join you.
He said; yes, that is what I'm doing, I'm gathering forces to fight against Muhammadﷺ.
So, Abdullah Bin Unais(عبدالله بن انيس) said I talked with him, for a while
until I felt confident that I can now attack
and I attacked him with my sword and killed him.
He said I left him with his women crouched over him, so he killed him.
It was laying on the ground and all of these women came swarming around the dead body.
And Abdullah Bin Unais(عبدالله بن انيس) left
and he enters Madina Rasool Allah ﷺ saw him and said;
اَفْلَحَ الْوَجْهْ
May this face succeed, he is making Dua(دعا) for Abdullah Bin Unais(عبدالله بن انيس).
Abdullah(عبدالله) said: I killed him.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Yes, you did.
You are speaking the truth.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ calls him indoors, he calls him into his house
and he gives him a stick.
So, Abdullah Bin Unais رضي الله عنه takes the stick and leaves.
His people met him and said,
Why did Rasool Allah give you this stick.
He said I don't know, he just gave it to me.
They said go back and ask him.
Why did they give you this stick?
Abdullah Bin Unais رضي الله عنه said, I went back
and I asked Rasool Allah ﷺ, Why did you give me this stick.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said this will be a sign between me and you, on the Day of Judgment.
Abdullah Bin Unais رضي الله عنه said;
I tied that stick to my sword, meaning it was always with me
and when he died, his instructions were to bury that stick with him
And it was wrapped with him, in his shroud and buried with him.
So that on the Day of Judgment, when he is resurrected
he can have that stick as a sign between him and Rasool Allah ﷺ.
And by the way, Rasool Allah ﷺ said in the Hadith(حديث).
And on that day, a few people will have something to lean on.
When he told him that I give you the stick
to be a sign between me and you on the Day of Judgment.
He also told him, And on that day few people will have something to lean on.
The scholars say that this means few people will have deeds on which to lean on, on the Day of Judgment.
And so, this is the story of the assassination of Khalid Bin Sufiaan Al-Hudali( خالد بن سفيان الهذلي).
And due to his assassination that ended the plan of Hudail(هذيل) to attack Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, it shows you that Rasool Allah did not choose to fight the tribe of Hudail(هذيل)
and rather he chose to assassinate Khalid(خالد),
because the problem was with Khalid(خالد) and to spare the blood of the people.
Rasool Allah ﷺ assassinated this single man because
some people might wonder, I mean, what are these political assassinations
that Rasool Allah ﷺ was involved in?
Well, that is to save the people from bloodshed rather than fighting the whole tribe
who would not have otherwise fight with Rasool Allah ﷺ if it wasn't for Khalid Bin Hudail( خالد بن الهذيل).
Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted to take care of this problem by reducing the bloodshed
and that is by killing this man, who is the cause of the whole problem.
This was a man with an outstanding personality
and ability to lead the people and he was leading them into evil.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ took him out of the way
and that spared the Muslims and the people of Hudail(هذيل) from war.
Rasool Allah ﷺ sends a group of 10 men for a mission and their leader was Asim Bin Thabit رضي الله عنه.
They reach to the land of Bannu Lahyaan(بنو لحيان),
and they are ambushed by 100 archers
so 100 against 10.
So, they fled to a small hill, they climb that hill or a rock,
and these hundred archers surrounded them.
The archers told them come down, we guarantee you that we wouldn't kill you.
We pledge that we wouldn't kill you, this is our word.
The Ameer(امير) said;
I do not accept the pledges of Mushrikeen(مشركين),
I do not accept your word, I do not accept your pledge.
And he chose to fight, this was the Ameer(امير), Asim Bin Thabit(عاصم بن ثابت).
So they fight, seven get killed.
So you have three remaining, they surrendered
and they were tied up in ropes.
One of them felt that they would be betrayed
and he was able to pull out his hand from the ropes
and he drew out his sword and tried to attack these men from Bannu Lahyaan(بنو لحيان).
But they kept a distance from him and kept on pelting him with rocks, until they killed him.
And they took the other two men and sold them to the people of Makkah.
These two men Khabbab(خَبَّاب) and Zaid Bin (الدثنة)Dathinnah رضي الله عنهما.
Now, obviously we would know what the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) would do with these two men,
they would kill them.
So, they decide that they're going to kill the two men.
They take them out of Makkah because Makkah is Haram(حرم)
and you are not supposed to kill in Makkah.
So they take them outside the boundaries of Makkah
and they ask these two men
they tell them would you wish that Muahmmad(محمد) is in your place and you are safe with your family.
They respond by saying, we don't wish to be safe with our family while Muhammadﷺ is hurt by a thorn
and we would rather die than Rasool Allah ﷺ being hurt.
Abu Sufiyan(ابو سفيان) said;
مَا رَاَيْتُ اَحَدًا يُحِبُّ اَحَدًا كَحُبِّ اَصْحَابْ مُحَمَّدِ مُحَمَّدًا
I've never seen a people, who love their leader
more than the people of Muahmmad(محمد), love him.
And I want to stop here and bring up this issue of loving Rasool Allah ﷺ.
The love of the Sahabah(صحابه) of Rasool Allah ﷺ was so true and so deep
that it was even known to the enemies of Muhammadﷺ.
So, here you have Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان) admitting, because it was so compelling,
the evidence was so clear, the issue was so impressive
that Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان), the leader of the enemies of Rasool Allah ﷺ admits publicly
and says, I've never seen people, who love someone like the Sahabah(صحابه) love Muhmmad(محمد).
And this wasn't because, see,
if the Sahabah(صحابه) would claim that they love Muhammadﷺ day and night,
that wouldn't have made a difference.
But the love of Muhammadﷺ emanated from their actions
it was reflected in their deeds.
Here you have two men facing death
and they were asked whether you wish to be safe
with your family, with your kids with your wife in the comfort of your home
and have Muhammadﷺ here instead of you, they said,
We would rather give our lives, than Muhammadﷺ be pricked by a thorn, be hurt by a thorn.
So, this issue of loving Muhammadﷺ was so well known to everyone.
They are both killed, as far as we know that, Khabbab(خَبَّاب), he was crucified.
And his body remained on that cross
until Ummayyah Bin Amr Adh-Dhamri(اُمَيَّةَ بن عَمْرُو اَلضَّمْرِيْ) comes and takes the body and buries it.
Khabbab رضي الله عنه before his death, he asks this woman
because he was held captive in the house of this woman, who lost her husband.
And they said that
it was Khabbab(خَبَّاب), who killed her husband in the Battle of Badr(بدر).
So, it was this family that was going to take revenge.
So he was in their house,
so he tells this woman can you bring me a steel blade
so that I can prepare myself for death.
What he wants to do with this blade is, to shave his pubic hair.
So, she sends him the blade with her child, young child.
In one narration it says that she gave it to him but then the child crawled onto the lap of Khabbab(خَبَّاب)
anyway doesn't make a difference.
The child ended up, in the hands in the lap of Khabbab(خَبَّاب)
When the woman sees child in Khabbab(خَبَّاب)'s lap
and he's holding this blade in his hand,
what would she think?
Khabbab(خَبَّاب) saw that she's worried that he might kill this child.
But he told her;
مَا كُنْتُ لِاَفْعَلْ ذَالِكَ اِنْشَاءَ الله
That's not something I would do.
In Sha Allah(ان شاءالله), that's not going to be something that I would do
And the lesson here to learn is that,
even though he was going to be killed by the Kuffar(كفار) that didn't make him take revenge on a child, an innocent child.
And a Muslim is not a traitor, a Muslim would not betray
and a Muslim would not take away the life of an innocent human being.
And even though he had a chance, and he already knew that he would be killed
he could have taken revenge from that child, but he didn't.
And that woman said, I've never seen a prisoner better than him
I would come in and see him eating from a plate full of grapes,
when there are no grapes in Makkah whatsoever
and I'm sure that he received those grapes from the angels.
This is what a Mushrik(مشرك) woman, who was saying,
Karamaat(كرامات).
Now another lesson also is that, it shows you
even though he was facing death, he still wanted to fulfill the Sunnah(سنة),
he was going to shave his pubic hair, which is one of the Sunnan(سنن) of Fitrah(فطرة).
He wanted to do that even though
you know, you could argue and say, well the Ummah(امة) has more important things to think about then shaving pubic hair.
I mean let's get serious and start taking care of the important things.
Well the Sahabah رضي الله عنه, they will take everything seriously.
Everything in Islam was serious to them,
so even though he's facing death, he still wants to follow the Sunnah(سنة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Also before he was crucified, he sought permission from his crucifiers.
He said, allow me to pray.
So, they did grant him time to pray.
He prayed two Rak'ah(ركعة).
When he finished he looked at them and said;
If it wasn't for the fear of you, accusing me of being afraid of death,
I would have making these two Rak'ah(ركعة) longer.
So, he made the Salah(صلاة) short, so that they wouldn't think that he's afraid of dying.
And he is the first one to start this Sunnah(سنة) of praying two Rak'ah(ركعة) before death.
Later on, it became a Sunnah(سنة) because of his action.
Khubaib رضي الله عنه was killed, and Zaid(زيد) was killed
and Abdullah Bin Tariq(عبدالله بن طارق) was killed.
So, now you have the entire group of 10 ended up dead, all of them.
Seven were killed on the spot
Abdullah Bin Tariq(عبد الله بن طارق) was killed on the way to Makkah
and the other two were killed in Makkah, so all of them were killed.
The Munafiqeen(منافقين) what they said was and this is according to Ibn Abbas(ابن عباس)
they said, How sad for those misguided people who died that way.
They neither stayed with their families, nor did they carry out their masters mission.
What the Munafiqeen(منافقين) are saying is that these 10 men are a failure.
They ended up dying for nothing, the mission wasn't accomplished
and they ended up losing their lives for nothing.
If they stayed home, it would have been better for them.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ revealed the Ayah(آية) saying,
وَمِنَ النَّاسِ مَنْ يُعْجِبُكَ قَوْلُهُ فِي الْحَيَاةِ الدُّنْيَا وَيُشْهِدُ اللَّهَ عَلَىٰ مَا فِي قَلْبِهِ وَهُوَ أَلَدُّ الْخِصَامِ۝
And of the people is, he whose speech pleases you in worldly life
and he calls Allah to witness as to what is in his heart
yet he is the fiercest of opponents.
So, this Ayah(آية) is talking about the Munafiqeen(منافقين)
and Allah says;
وَمِنَ النَّاسِ مَنْ يَشْرِي نَفْسَهُ ابْتِغَاءَ مَرْضَاتِ اللَّهِ ۗ وَاللَّهُ رَءُوفٌ بِالْعِبَادِ۝
And of the people is he, who sells himself seeking means to the approval of Allah
and Allah is kind to His servants
And this is the Aayah(آية) talking about these 10 men
that they sold themselves to Allah.
It doesn't make a difference if they achieved the mission or not
these men have given their lives for Allahعَزّوجَل.
So, they will be credited for that and they will be rewarded by Allahعَزّوجَلّ greatly.
And what the Munafiqeen(منافقين) are saying could come in different forms.
I mean, they could have presented it in the form of these men don't have Hikmah(حكمه).
If they had Hikmah(حكمه), they wouldn't have killed themselves in such a way.
These men were, they were rash, and
they should not went out and taking this unnecessary risk.
But all of these ways of saying it, are missing the important point here
and that is what was your Niyyah(نية).
The Niyyah(نية) of these men was right,
therefore they died Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله عَزُّوجَل).
Whether the mission was accomplished or not,
it doesn't affect the validity of that Niyyah(نية).
The Niyyah(نية) was appropriate, the Niyyah(نية) was right
and that is how Allahعَزّوجَلّ accepts the deed, from a person.
Not every mission will be successful not every battle will be won.
But Allahعَزّوجَلّ holds you accountable to your Niyyah(نية),
what was the Niyyah(نية).?
Another event that occurred between the Battle of Uhud(أحَد) and Al-Khandaq(الخندق), is Bier Maoonah(بئر معونة).
One of the leaders of the tribes of Najd(نجد) came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and said,
Islam is spreading among my people, I want you to send me preachers
who would call to Islam Dua'ah(دعوات).
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ send over 70 men.
These men were called the Al-Qur'rah(القرآء), the reciters of Qur'an.
They would work during the day by selling wood
and they would spend the night in the Qiyyaam Ul Lail(قيام اليل), in reciting Qur'an.
This was their life.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ sends them over to teach these people about Islam.
So they are Dua'ah(دعوات) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله),
and they were given a guarantee of safety by this man, Abul Bara'a(ابو البرآء),
who's called Mala'a Bin Athinna(ملاعب بن الاَسنة).
When they reach to his territory.
His nephew, Amir Bin Tufail(عامر بن طفيل) invites the men of his tribe to fight against the seventy Qur'a(قرآء).
So, his uncle refuses, but he is successful in bringing up a force sufficient to attack these 70 men.
Now this Amir Bin Tufail(عامر بن طفيل) has already met with Rasool Allah ﷺ previously
and he told him;  O, Muahmmad(محمد), I give you three alternatives.
Number one, you become king over the towns and I become king over the Bedouin people,
as if this issue is all about kingdom.
Number two you make me a Khalifah(خليفه), after you.
You announced that when you die, I become king after you.
Third choice if you refused, number one and two
I'll attack you, with an army of 2000 men.
Rasool Allah ﷺ refused obviously would not even talk to respond to us nonsense.
So he was upset.
This is one of the reasons, why he wanted to attack and kill these 70 men
and they were massacred.
These 70 men were massacred, a great disaster.
When the news reached to Rasool Allah ﷺ,
it was immediately conveyed, when the news was reached to Rasool Allah ﷺ
Rasool Allah ﷺ was greatly affected by that news
and was very sad about what happened and the betrayal of these people.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ starts making Dua Al-Qanoot(دعا القنوت)
and Dua Al-Qanoot(دعا القنوت) was never done before.
This was the first time Rasool Allah ﷺ does Dua Al-Qanoot(دعا القنوت)
and he would do it in Fajr(فجر), Zhuhar(ظهر) Asar(عصر), Maghrib(مغرب) and Ish'a(عشاء) in every salah(صلاة)
and he would make Dua(دعا) against those people
against the Raql(ركل) and Zaqwaan(ذكوان) and Lahyaan(لحيان) and these tribes
that betrayed the Muslims and kill them in such cold blood.
Rasool Allah ﷺ would make this Dua(دعا) in his Salah(صلاة), in every Salah.
Now Haraam Bin Malhaan(حرام بن ملحان), who was the Ameer(امير) of the group,
when he was talking to Amir Bin Tufail(عامر بن طفيل).
Amir Bin Tufail(عامر بن طفيل) gives signal to one of his men to go and kill him.
So this man, his name is Jabbar(جبار), he sneaks from behind Haraam(حرام),
and he stabs him with his spear in his back.
And the blade comes out from the chest of Haraam(حرام).
So, you can imagine Haraam(حرام) standing here
and staring down and seeing this blade sticking out from his chest.
What does he say? Oh, my God, I'm dead.
Oh, no, look what happened to me I'm worried about my kids.
What does he say?
His response was shocking to those present
He said;
الله اكبر فُزْتُ وَرَبُّ الْكَعْبَه
Allah is great, I have won,
I have succeeded in the name of the Lord of Ka'aba(كعبه),
I've succeeded.
That is what he said before he falls down as a Shaheed(شهيد).
Now, this was a shocking statement to make.
I mean man, you're suffering out of that pain, and your blood is gushing out of your wound.
It says another narration that his hands were soaked in blood.
And he takes the blood and he wipes it on his head and his face.
And he says, I've succeeded in the name of Allah
The man who killed him, would later on say
when he's telling the story of how he became Muslim, he said;
I stabbed the man from behind and spear came out from his chest.
And he said, Allah is great, I have succeeded by the name of the Lord of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
So, I went around asking, What is he talking about?
What do you mean, you succeeded?
I killed you, he's dead.
How can you say that he succeeded?
They told him, he's talking about Shahadah(شهادة).
He is talking about becoming a martyr.
He has succeeded, he has succeeded in becoming a Shaheed(شهيد)
and then they explain to him what Shaheed(شهيد) means.
He said, and that's when I became Muslim.
I said, Man, he has truly won, yes, he did!
نَعْمْ لَقَدْ اَفْلَحْ
When he understood where this Muslim is coming from,
when he understood, what the concept of Shahadah(شهادة) is, he said, yes,
that makes sense now, he did succeed, and he became Muslim.
Subhaan Allah(سبحان الله), you know,
Haraam Bin Malhaan(حرام ابن ملحان) dies as a Shaheed(شهيد)
and he also is giving Da'wah(دعوة), in his Shahadah(شهاده) and somebody is becomes Muslim because of that.
His own assassin, becomes Muslim,
because of those last words of Haraam Bin Malhaan(حرام بن ملحان),
so not only is he a Shaheed(شهيد), but he's also a Daiyah(داعية), even in his last moments.
That's the Barakah(بركة) that Allahعَزّوجَلّ has given to Haraam رضي الله عنه,
I mean, you never know what's gonna bring people closer to Islam.
I mean, who would have imagined that the statement made by Haraam(حرام)
would actually be the reason for somebody becoming Muslim.
Amir Bin Fuhairah(عامر بن فهيره), was one of these men
You might remember the name of Aamir(عامر) from Hijrah(هجره).
He was the servant of Abu Bakr(ابو بكر).
He also accompanied them in the journey of Hijrah(هجرة).
He was also the shepherd, who would bring the goats to the cave,
when Rasool Allah ﷺ and Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) were in hiding.
So, Aamir(عامر) was one of these 70 men and he was killed.
By the way, I should have mentioned that only one of the 70 men,  his life was spared
and that is Amr Bin Ummayyah Adh-Dhamri(عمرو بن امية الضمري).
They captured him, and he was freed
because, when Amir Bin Tufail(عامر بن طفيل) knew that he is from Mudhar(مضر).
The mother of Aamir(عامر) had made an oath that
she is going to free a man from Mudhar(مضر).
So, Aamir(عامر) said since this man is from Mudhar(مضر), we're going to free him
and that would fulfill the oath of my mother.
So, he was freed.
Aamir(عامر) said, when they captured me, they pointed out to me
a dead body of one of the 70 men
and they said whose body is this?
I told them, this is the body of Amir Bin Fuhairah(عامر بن فهيره).
They said, when he was killed his body, went up in the sky and then came down.
His body rose up in the sky
and stayed there for a while and then it came down the angels sort of lifted him up.
So, that's a Karamah(كرمة) that happened with Amir Bin Fuhairah(عامر بن فهيره).
Forgot to mention something about Asim Bin Thabit(عاصم بن ثابت),
Asim Bin Thabit(عاصم بن ثابت) go back to Rajiah(رجيعة),
Asim Bin Thabit(عاصم بن ثابت) before he was killed.
He said; See because he refused to give up.
He said I'm not gonna take the pledge from Kuffar(كفار).
When they were killing his men,
they were stripping them naked, they would take everything off them.
So, Asim(عاصم), said: O Allah
as I fought for your religion when I'm alive, protect my body when I'm dead.
He didn't want them to strip him like they would do with the rest of his men.
So, he made that Dua(دعا) to Allahعَزّوجَلّ
when he died they wanted to come and strip him.
In addition to that they also wanted to cut off his head because
there was a woman whose sons were killed by Asim Bin Thabit(عاصم بن ثابت).
So, she made an oath that if someone would bring her, the skull of Asim Bin Thabit(عاصم بن ثابت)
she would pay him 100 camels
and she would drink wine in his skull.
So, these men knew that the skull of this man is worth 100 camels,
so they really want wanted to get it.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ sends a swarm of wasps to protect the body of Asim(عاصم)
and whenever somebody would come close to him the wasp would jump on him and sting him.
So, they said let's leave him and come and claim his body tomorrow.
At night Allahعَزّوجَلّ sends a flood that takes the body away
and the body disappears and they couldn't find him.
So, this is a Karamah(كرامة) that happened with Asim Bin Thabit رضي الله عنه.
We'll carry on in Sha Allah ho Ta'ala(اِنْ شَاء الله تعالى),
with some other events that happened between Uhud(أحَد) and Al-Khandaq(اَلْخَنْدق) tomorrow.
رَبَّنَا آتِنَا فِي الدُّنْيَا حَسَنَةً وَفِي الْآخِرَةِ حَسَنَةً وَقِنَا عَذَابَ النَّارِ
وَصَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرًا
وَالسلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته